<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>thelastpointer</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on thelastpointer</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 13:28:53 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>github.io</title>
      <link>/posts/githubio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 13:28:53 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/githubio/</guid>
      <description>New Site!
I&amp;rsquo;m pretty excited to try github.io for a personal landing page.
I got inspired by Forrest Smith&amp;rsquo;s post on leaving Medium; he opted for a simple, static website that is easy to control and easier on the user. Recently, a lot of opinions surfaced about the web being bloated, and I fully agree.
&amp;quot;Why do I need a 4Ghz quadcore to run facebook?&amp;quot; This is why. A single word split up into 11 HTML DOM elements to avoid adblockers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Awesome Blog: Dan Luu (danluu.com)</title>
      <link>/posts/awesome-blog-danluu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2019 14:08:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/awesome-blog-danluu/</guid>
      <description>I found a great post at danluu.com. I strongly recommend it! The author explores player interactions from male and female perspectives. What I found captivating is the methodical, data-driven, scientific way he presented his findings. More of this please! His other posts are great too, and cover a wide variety of topics.
Since then, I&amp;rsquo;ve been devouring his posts, and it&amp;rsquo;s all kinds of fascinating. It&amp;rsquo;s rare to find a blog so good, so I decided to write an endorsement post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I tried node.js &#43; Heroku</title>
      <link>/posts/nodejs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 10:13:03 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/nodejs/</guid>
      <description>y So I decided to try NodeJS and Heroku.
Heroku is a service that hosts your applications. NodeJS is a&amp;hellip; well, you know what it is, right? You create apps using javascript, that&amp;rsquo;s what it is.
There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of hype around these two, so I was curious to try them; I also come from a very different environment (desktop apps written in C#) so I expected nothing &amp;ndash; other than my own incompetence :) I knew I needed to learn this from scratch basically, so I tried to enter this world with no preconceptions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First</title>
      <link>/posts/first/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 11:23:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/first/</guid>
      <description>yo man! This is my first post with hugo. i like it so far.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pro stuff</title>
      <link>/pro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 11:23:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/pro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is basically my CV, but with more pictures :) Images open a gallery, check them out!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prototypes and personal stuff</title>
      <link>/proto/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 11:23:21 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/proto/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;These are things I made for fun, to try new things, but mostly because they had something to do with my plans to conquer the world.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 16:10:42 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Hi! I&amp;rsquo;m László, I program games in Unity. I like prototyping ideas. I also like spaceships, books, spices, music with guitars. I&amp;rsquo;m a dog person and my favorite game is Unreal from 1998.
Contact https://twitter.com/thelastpointer/
Fun facts  I once wrote an operating system. I started programming because I wanted to hack Starcraft maps. I failed a class at uni because I obfuscated my homework. It worked flawlessly. I wrote a simple roguelike for VAX-11/VMS.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>